Guide to the Ida Klaus Papers WAG.161
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ida Klaus Papers
1954-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Klaus, Ida, 1905-1999
WAG.161
17.25 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 2 oversize folders.
Ida Klaus (1905-1999) was born in Brownsville, Brooklyn and organized her first union as a teenager while working at a hotel in Saratoga Springs, NY. Klaus went on to work first for the National Labor Relations Board and then the New York City Department of Labor. Klaus was the author of the "Little Wagner Act," which gave city employees the right to organize and bargain collectively, and also wrote the first detailed code of labor relations for city employees. In the early 1960s Klaus negotiated the first citywide teachers' contract in the country on behalf of the New York City Board of Education. The materials document Ida Klaus' work with labor unions as an arbitrator and attorney, primarily in New York City but also in other states and Puerto Rico. The collection is comprised of newsletters, briefs, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, drafts, transcripts of speeches, and research notes.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Ida Klaus (1905-1999) was born in Brownsville, Brooklyn and organized her first union as a teenager while working at a hotel in Saratoga Springs, NY. Klaus graduated from Hunter College and the Teachers Institute of the Jewish Theological Seminary of America. She was initially denied entry to the Columbia University Law School because she was a woman, but later became part of the first class accepting women and graduated in 1931. Klaus went on to work first for the National Labor Relations Board and then the New York City Department of Labor. Klaus was the author of the "Little Wagner Act," which gave city employees the right to organize and bargain collectively, and also wrote the first detailed code of labor relations for city employees. In the early 1960s Klaus negotiated the first citywide teachers' contract in the country on behalf of the New York City Board of Education.
Klaus was involved in notable negotiations between unions that represent teachers, steelworkers, postal workers, railroad workers and local and federal government. She served on the Arbitration Law committee for the American Arbitration Association, International Labor Relations Law committee of the American Bar Association, Columbia Law School Board of Visitors.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ida Klaus, 1998. The accession number associated with this gift is 1998.018.
Related Archival Materials
New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection (OH 001) contains an oral history interview with Ida Klaus.
Scope and Contents
The materials document Ida Klaus' work with labor unions as an arbitrator and attorney, primarily in New York City but also in other U.S. states and Puerto Rico. The collection is comprised of newsletters, briefs, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, drafts, transcripts of speeches, and research notes. Many of the materials in the collection relate to her work with the Arbitration Law committee for the American Arbitration Association, the International Labor Relations Laww committee of the American Bar Association, and the Columbia Law School Board of Visitors.
Collective labor agreements -- Lawyers.; Labor laws and legislation -- New York (State); Collective bargaining -- New York (State) -- New York.; Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Arbitration (Administrative law); United States. National Labor Relations Board; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; Klaus, Ida, 1905-1999; American Arbitration Association; United States. National Mediation Board; American Bar Association; New York (State). Public Employment Relations Board
- United Transportation Union vs. Long Island Rail Road & Metropolitan Transportation Authority Supreme Court briefs; memos, press releases, newspaper clippings, transcripts and related documents for the National Mediation Board Emergency Board Numbers 190, 191 and 192; Public Employment Relations Board newsletters; Long Island Railroad Public Law Board memos and notes, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
- Notes, agendas, and travel correspondence for the annual meetings of the Committee of International Labor Relations Law of the American Bar Association, 1985-1998 (Box 2)
- Notes, agendas, and travel correspondence for the annual meetings of the American Arbitration Association (1981-1985); General counsel annual reports for the American Arbitration Association (1977-1984); Arbitration awards, decisions and negotiations (1973-1985) (Box 3)
- Significant Office of Collective Bargaining decisions (1978-1979); Recommendations for legislation (1978-1979); Meeting notes from the Columbia Law School Board of Visitors meetings (1992-1996); 1980 transit strike correspondence; Parity case memos, notes, briefs and decisions (1974-1976); Public Employment Relations Board court decisions, memos, and notes (1977-1982), 1974-1996 (Box 4)
- Oral history transcript New York State School of Industrial Labor Relations at Cornell University; Ad hoc arbitrations (1977-1985); New York State PERB correspondence, memos and decisions (1982-1984); National Railroad Adjustment Board notes, memos awards and decisions (1965-1985); Agreements and arbitrations for railroad employee unions (Box 5)
- Speech transcripts from the annual Public Employment and Collective Bargaining conferences (1965-1966); Memos (1977-1979); Personal and legal correspondence (1972-1979); PERB newsletter (1979); Annual reports and newsletters form arbitration and labor relations organizations (1974-1982); Transcripts and articles of note (1962-1985) (Box 6)
- Memos and files related to cases reviewed by the Public Employment Relations Board (PERB) (1979-1989); PERB reappointment files (1981,1983); PERB swearing in photographs and related press; Files, agendas, minutes and memos from the Annual Meeting of the National Academy of Arbitrators (1984-1989); Pre-publication excerpts from "Between Management and Labor: Oral Histories of Arbitration" (1995); National Archive research files (1995-1996), 1979-1996 (Box 7)
- Research files, arbitration award, memorandums and correspondence related to cases reviewed by the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) and the Public Employment Relations Board (PERB) (1961-1985); Cosmopolitan club programs and correspondence (1987-1997); Arbitration Decisions L-R (1963-1973); Arbitration Decisions S-Z (1963-1974), 1961-1997 (Box 8)
- Federal Mediation Conciliation Services (FMCS) correspondence materials (1976-1981); Board of Arbitration awards and decisions (1971-1980); American Arbitration Association forms and correspondence; Airlines arbitrations and decisions (1976-1982) (Box 9)
- FMCS decisions (1979-1983); Board of Arbitration awards and decisions (1977-1979); United Federation of Teachers and the Board of Education arbitrations (1974-1975), 1974-1983 (Box 10)
- Labor relations research and memos; Rock article research and drafts (1961-1967); Speech drafts and research notes (1966-1969); Address presented at the 12th Annual Conference of Labor at NYU (1966); National Association of Secondary School Principals (NASSP) materials (1978), 1961-1969 (Box 11)
- NASSP Conference materials (1968); Samuel Klaus funeral remarks (1963); American Bar Association materials (1963-1965); PERB decisions (1974); Speech to school board attorneys (1987); International Industrial Relations Association preliminary reports and monographs (1954), 1954-1974 (Box 12)
- New York City collective bargaining executive orders (1955); Research notes and transcripts of speeches (1969-1975); Notes, programs and transcripts from Columbia Law School seminars (1962-1976); John Herling's Labor Letter's newsletters (1974); Research notes and speech to NASA executives; Michigan Law Review article and research (1969); Briefs, United Federation of Teachers demands (1975), 1955-1967 (Box 13)
- National Railroad Adjustment Board (NRAB) drafts, awards and decisions (1972-1989); Special Board of Adjustments (1964); Metro North arbitration and notes (1985), 1972-1985 (Box 14)
- Report on steelworkers presentation, research files, awards (1974); Correspondence (1975); Board of Arbitration cases; General Services Administration supplement (1981, 1985); National Academy of Arbitrators meeting materials (1990-1993), 1974-1993 (Box 15)
- Board of Arbitration awards, decisions, memos and notes; Agreements for teachers, postal workers and steel worker unions; Classroom teachers agreement (1955-1975) (Box 16)
- Abstracts of arbitration decisions (1961-1963); Arbitration Decisions A-F (1963-1974); Arbitration Decisions G-K (1963-1974), 1961-1974 (Box 17)
- Oversized Panoramic Photograph, June 1923 (Flat-file-folder 4, Tray 1)
- Oversized Magazine (Box Shared Tamiment 066, Folder 1)